你好黑客
hello hackers
欢迎回到高级漏洞利用模块
welcome back to the Advanced Exploitation Module
在这个视频中，我们将讨论
in this video we're going to be talking about
针对这个例子的完整利用过程
end to end pwnage of our motivating example
一个多线程消息存储服务
a multi threaded message storing service
我们在前4个视频中已经把它讲透了
that in the last four videos we have thoroughly dumped
目前情况如下
so status report
已知线程arena位置
we know where the thread specific arena is
哦，稍等
oh and hold on
我忘了标libc位置
I forgot to mark off where libc is
实际上，马上会讲到
actually let's get to that
我们已知线程arena地址
we know where the thread specific arena is
而且我们有以下能力
and we have the follow capabilities
可以泄露连接线程tcache_perthread_struct地址
we have the tcache perthread struct address disclosure for our connection thread
这让我们得到了这个
that got us this
还有我们前面讲的任意读和任意写
we have an arbitrary read and an arbitrary write that we've gone over previously
我们开始利用吧
so let's make things happen
我们要做这些
here's what we're going to do
首先要获取信息
first we're going to get all of our knowledge
这是上个视频中的脚本
this is the script from the last video
我们要尽可能的获取这些待搜集信息
you're going to get all the knowledge we want as much of these check marks as we can
先看看要泄露或计算的变量
let's take a look at what variable to leak and compute first
我们用这个竞争条件泄露出了perthread_struct地址
so we leaked the perthread struct using that awesome race condition
基于它计算出了线程arena中指向main_arena的指针
we computed based on that where a pointer to the main arena is stored on the thread's arena metadata
并用另一个竞争条件，实现了任意读
and using our race condition in a different way we got an arbitrary read
泄露出了main_arena地址
to leak out the main arena address itself
这是什么地址呢
what the hell is this address
这是一个libc内部的地址
well this is an address inside libc
具体来说，main_arena元数据位于libc的bss段
specifically the main arena metadata is in the BSS segment of libc
当然，它到libc基址的偏移值是常量
which is of course a constant offset of the base of libc where libc is loaded
我们启用GDB，以便查看
let's enable GDB so we can look around
好了，开始吧
okay here we go
泄露出了，成功了
leak a boom
就是这个
here it is
这是泄露出的信息
this is what we've leaked
下面是内存映射
here are the mappings
我们泄露的信息就在这个地址
what we leaked is in this address
确认无误
perfect amazing all right
能用减法算出它到libc基址之间的距离
we can figure out what the distance between that and the base of libc is using subtraction
结果就是这个
and it is this
它不会变
and it'll always be this
现在我们知道libc加载在哪了
so now we know where libc is
删了这段代码
let's take this off
这段代码没用
this serves no purpose of course
我们之前用aaaacccc覆盖了它，这只是为了展示任意写
we also have overwrote it with aaaacccc but that was just for show
现在你知道libc在哪里了
so now you know where the libc is
libc基址 = main_arena地址 - 它
the libc base is the main arena address minus that
很好
amazing all right so
这个内存映射还告诉了我们什么
what else does that tell us
首先，告诉了我们所有其他库的加载位置
this tells us first of all where all of the other libraries are loaded
因为它们彼此之间都有固定的偏移值
because they're all loaded at these constant offsets of each other
这很好
which is great
但它还告诉了我们一件有趣的事
but it also tells us one more interesting thing actually
它告诉了我们内存映射基址
it tells us the memory mapping base
即ASLR后库加载的基址
that address space layout randomization base where all the libraries are loaded
还告知了所有普通的内存映射都映射在相邻的位置
but also where all of the memory mapped allocations in general are adjacently mapped in
这包括我们的线程数据，比如线程结构
right and this includes our thread data such as the thread struct
线程堆有被随机化
now the thread heap has some randomization built in
但幸运的是，线程结构没有
but the thread struct luckily does not
如果检查一下我们的线程
if you look at our threads
我的脚本创建了3个连接
my script makes 3 connections
1 2 3
虽然我们只用这两个
although we only ever use these two
我也不知道为啥创建这第三个
so I don't know why we do the third one
但不管怎样，这也ok
but anyways that's fine so here we go
线程2
thread 2
线程1是主线程，它在那里等待连接请求
thread 1 is the main thread that is sitting there waiting for connections
线程2、3和4是连接处理线程
thread 2 3 and 4 are our awesome connection handler threads
如果我们切换到线程2
if we switch to thread 2
然后回退
and we scroll up
用bt看一下子线程调用栈
so of course the back trace of this our call stack
目标在vuln
it's up at vuln
一直回退到vuln
let's go all the way up to vuln
这是我们的那个有漏洞的函数
this is our vulnerable function
gdb好用的一点是，它知道这个栈帧中的rbp
in here GDB is nice enough to figure out what RBP should be in this function
你可以查看它
so you can actually examine it
在RBP+8处，是到handle_connection里的返回地址
at RBP+ 8 is going to be the return address into handle connection
然后，线程将在这里退出
and then of course that's where the thread will exit
如果我们能覆盖这个地址
but if we can overwrite this address
我们就能劫持控制流
then we have hijacked control flow
幸运的是
luckily
这个地址到libc基址的偏移值是常量
that address is a constant offset off of libc
就是4138
and it's that 4138
所以我们甚至知道线程2（口误）中栈上存RIP的地址
so we even know where the stored rip address for thread 1 is
它在libc基址 - 0x4138
it's at libc base minus 0x4138
仅仅是通过泄漏libc
just by leaking libc
我们计算出了libc基址
so now let's say we computed the libc base
我会区分什么是计算的，什么是泄露的
I'd like to get track of what I've computed and what I've leaked
这不仅有助于教学
it's nice for teaching
也有助于快速发现
but it's also nice to quickly understand
是基于前面的泄露结果，计算出错了
if you have a computation that's wrong based on previous leak
还是泄露出错了
or you have a leak that's wrong
当然
and of course
现在执行脚本，能得到这些
if we run we can get these
实际上还能知道一个信息
you can get actually one more thing
请注意stored_rip_address中的值
you notice at this stored rip address
它是一个text段的地址
is an address into our binary
现在我们甚至可以得到PIE基址了
so now we can even get the pie base
当然还是用我们的任意读
using our arbitrary read again of course
addr_in_binary就在handle_connection指令中
see addr_in_binary somewhere in handle connection
我们读出stored_rip_address中的值
we read out the stored rip address
我们就可以算出text段的基址
and we can of course calculate the base of the binary
用这个值减去gdb中获取的text段基址
by taking this and subtracting that
获取固定偏移量 0x17f
that's 17f into the binary
现在我们甚至知道了text段基址
now we can even say binary base
我们现在可以输出更多东西了
okay so now we can print more stuff
现在我们基本上已经看透了
and we know basically everything at this point
我们禁用GDB并运行
let's disable GDB and run
首次泄漏失败
the initial leak failed
怎么了
what's going on here
大概是这几次运气不好
okay we just got unlucky several times I think
看看这个
all right check this out
我们泄露出了main_arena地址
we leaked the main arena address
这个已经做过无数次了
we've done this a million times now
在此基础上，我们计算出了libc基址
based on that we computed the libc base
它以000结尾，这看起来很好
this looks pretty good in the sense that it ends in 000
当然我们可以调出maps
and of course we'll read out our own maps
确认它是匹配的
so we can actually confirm that it does match
在此基础上，我们找出了stored_rip_address
based on that we figured out where the stored instruction pointer is
它作为返回地址，存储在子线程的栈上
where the return address is stored on the thread stack
这是子线程栈上的地址
this is an address into the thread stack
我们泄露出它的值，以找出text段中的地址
we leak that out to figure out an address in the binary
是一个返回到handle_connection中的返回地址
in the return address into the handle connection function
并依此算出text段基址
and based on that we figure out where the binary base is
注意，一个经验是
again rule of thumb
当你的计算正确时
when your calculations are correct
页面基址的末尾会是000
you'll have a 000 at the base of all pages
当然
of course
这并不能保证其余部分都是正确的
this doesn't guarantee that the rest is correct
但至少是一个快速的烟雾测试
but at least it's a quick smoke test
这之后呢
now what
已经可以宣告成功了
well now guys we're done
我们知道栈在哪里
we know where the stack is
知道返回地址在哪里
we know where the return address is
假如说我们不知道canary
for example if we don't know the canary
但能知道
we could
我们能任意读
we have an arbitrary read
而canary就在这个地址前16字节处
the canary is 16 bytes before this address
哦不对，在这个地址前
no before this address
但其实，我们都不需要知道它
but we don't even need to
我们可以直接覆盖返回地址
we can overwrite directly from the return address
我们可以任意写
and we have an arbitrary write
任意写可以直接覆盖返回地址
that'll allow us to do that
这太不可思议了
right so this is incredible
我们现在
let's of course now
我们先看一下当前进度
actually let's do a quick status check
知道了很多东西
know a lot of stuff
现在的计划是什么
what's the plan now
我们在这一步
we are here
我们要这么做
we're going to do this
可以泄露出canary，从溢出点覆盖到返回地址
we can either leak the canary and overflow the whole stack
提醒一下
as a reminder
在这个输入的scanf处有一个溢出点
there's an overflow right here in this input scanf
但这工作量太大了
but that's too much work
我们直接用rop链覆盖返回地址
we're just gonna overwrite the return address directly with a ROP chain as I said
我们开始吧
so let's do it
我们要
here we go we are going to
输出：let's roll
print let's roll
有些人喜欢
some more into
在利用程序中彰显个性
for your exploits to have some personality
你甚至可以这样做
you can even do this
这很好
that's pretty good all right
我们开始吧
okay so we're rolling
从pwntools中取一个表示libc的elf实例
grab an ELF instance from pwntools representing libc
我要用pwntools来自动生成ROP链
one thing I'm about to do is use pwntools to auto generate the ROP chain
有时ROP很困难，缺少很多条件
ropping in constrained situations happens
但通常，当你有了足够的原语，足够的信息
but very frequently once you build up enough primitives enough knowledge
就很容易了
you can go the easy way right
现在就是这样的情况
in this case that is one such case
我们设置好libc基址
we're gonna set the libc base
所以现在
so now and
在用pwntools生成ROP链时，别忘了
very important when you're generating ROP chains with pwntools don't forget
或者说做任何复杂的事时，不要忘了设置架构
or doing anything complicated don't forget to set your architecture
我们还没设置
we haven't done that yet
我会创建一个ROP
I'll create a ROP guy
但我不会光用pwntools创建一个默认ROP对象
but I'm not just gonna create a ROP object with pwntools
pwntools真的很好
pwntools is really nice
因为它支持过滤掉ROP链中的一些字符
in that it supports filtering out some characters in your ROP chain
或者说能让ROP链中不含一些特定的字符
or being careful to make a ROP chain that doesn't have certain characters in it
我们在这里忽视了一点
one thing we've loss over in all of this is that
程序用printf和scanf读取我们给的地址、所有数据
the program uses printf and scanf to read in our addresses all of our data
这是一个问题，因为printf和scanf将在空格处停止读取
this is the problem because printf and scanf will stop at white space
所以要避免带有所有类型的空格
so we have to avoid all white space all spaces
我们必须避免换行符
we also have to avoid new lines
回车和其他一些东西
carriage returns and a bunch of other stuff right
垂直制表符，水平制表符等
vertical tabs tabs etc
pwntools很好，能过滤掉这些
pwntools is really nice that it lets you do that
否则你就要用grep
otherwise you will have to you know grep
在你的ROP链搜索器中用grep排除这些
exclude things using grep in your rop chain finder
现在只需给pwntools设置好要过滤的
all right so then we just set that to pwntools and
我们就不用考虑这些了
we don't have to think about it
我们做一个快速测试
let's run a quick test
只执行 exit 42
just exit 42
整个ROP链就这些
that'll be our entire rop chain
然后把它写入栈上的返回地址
and we're gonna write it into our stored rip address over the stack
基本上就好了
boom and we're basically done
如何触发它呢
so how do we trigger that
只需终止线程
of course we terminate the thread
我们发送quit，使vuln函数返回
we send quit so that vuln returns
它会返回到它以为的handle_connection函数
it'll return to what it thinks would be handle connection
但实际上返回到了ROP链
but is actually a ROP chain
我们在这个进程wait一下
and then we're going to wait on this process
打印出退出码
and print out what it exited with
应该是42
and this should be 42
好了，我们开始吧
all right let's roll
忘了右括号，好了，开始吧
forget to close parentheses all right let's roll
计算,泄漏
computed computing leaks
崩溃
crash
啊，我们的任意写需要一个整数参数
ah our arbitrary write assumes an integer input
我们就在这用了它
it is the only place we use it
scanf可以接受任意长的输入
and scanf can take an arbitrarily long input or whatever the format string must to
我们把这个改成直接发送值
so we're actually gonna change this to just send the value directly
只要那里没有空格，就没问题
as long as there are no spaces there we're good to go
我的意思是
I mean yeah
因为这个，我们知道这里没有空格
and there and we know there are no spaces because of that
我们不再传入整数给任意写
so instead of passing an integer to our arbitrary write
再编码，转成小端序
and then encoding it and then packing it in little endian
我们直接传入字节
we're just going to send bytes directly
很好，按回车键
all right perfect hit enter
好的，参数超出范围
okay argument out of range
因为泄露perthread_struct失败了
because we fail to leak the perthread struct
是有这种情况
it happens
开始吧
here we go
好了，我们开始吧
all right let's roll
砰砰砰退出码是42
boom boom boom exited 42
我们可以代码执行了
we have code execution
执行了ROP链
ROP chain we're done
当然，我们来完善这个ROP链
of course let's do this ROP chain
我们需要字符串：/flag
it hmm we need the word flag
想要打开/flag文件
I want to smoothly open the flag
需要从可控标准输入中，读入/flag字符串
so we're going to read the word flag from standard in which we control
能通过连接的文件描述符，写入数据到libc的bss段
we could use any of the connection file descriptors into the libc BSS
它对我们来说只是临时可读可写的数据段
this is just temporary readable writable data for us
libc会使用它
libc use it for something
但这是一个很大的bss段
but there's a big BSS
在完成利用前，所用数据被破坏的可能很小
the chances that we'll corrupt something that we need before down to our exploit is low
我们直接用libc函数
and we're using the libc functions
尽管已知libc地址，里面有gadget能调用系统调用
even though we have libc and there are syscall gadgets in there
但这样简单多了，pwntools处理得更好
this is much easier pwntools handles it a lot better
我们打开/flag文件
all right we'll open that
调用sendfile从文件描述符3发到标准输出
we will send file from the third file descriptor to standard out
只是，我们不能假设文件描述符3可用
except for the third file descriptor is not something that we can assume
在很简单的程序中，可以
in very simple programs it is
但是在任何复杂的程序中
but in any complex program
就比如这个，用一个描述符接收连接
such as this one which uses a file descriptor to listen further connection
再针对每个连接用一个来通信
then uses a file descriptor per connection to actually speak to the client and so forth
所以这里的文件描述符大概是
this file descriptor is probably going to be
因为我们打开了三个连接
because we open three connections
但我们不用担心这个
but let's not worry about it
我们先关了文件描述符3
let's close file descriptor 3
那么下一个，这里open的，就是3了
so that the next this one that's open is gonna be 3
这样写的话，我们不能新建连接了
so with this we can't connect again
否则 3 将被占用
that's the accept file descriptor
但谁在乎呢
but who cares all right
这样应该能泄露出flag
and then this should leak as the flag
这里p.wait改成
so let's instead of p.wait we will
readall 开始吧
readall  here we go
这里在等我们发送/flag
and it's waiting for us to send flag
我的锅
my bad
好的，现在发送了/flag
here we go now we send slash flag
它被读入到libc的bss中
that gets read into the BSS
然后 open、sendfile、exit
and then you open send file exit
好的
boom
我们的flag在这里
there is our flag
很酷吧
how cool is that
要点是
so takeaway is here
当我们能任意读、任意写时
once we had arbitrary read and arbitrary write
距离成功就很近了
it was pretty simple to get to game over
但是为了做到这一点
but in order to do that
我们需要在内存中探索
we had to do some sleuthing around memory
经过本模块的课后题，你将成为这方面的专家
you will become an expert in sleuthing around memory with these challenge problems for this module
还有一个有趣的点
and an interesting takeaway is
我们的任意写实际上是有限制的
our arbitrary write actually had a limit a limitation
这个限制是非常具体的
that limitation was very specific it was
我们不能写入空格
the fact that we could not write white spaces
完全没办法
there's no way
在任意写或任意读时，你将经常面对这些限制
often times you'll be faced with these limitations on arbitrary write or an arbitrary read
实际上我们的任意读、写还有一个限制
actually our arbitrary read and write also had another limitation
因为我们用scanf读取想要的地址
in that because we used scanf to read in the address we wanted right here
你同样也不能用含有能被解析成空格字符的地址值
you also couldn't use any addresses that have any white space characters in the address
假如我们的地址值中含有0x20
so if our address had a hex 20 in it
就写入不了这个地址值
we can't do it
这很棘手
so that's tricky
我说到哪了
what was I yeah
这在利用开发中并不罕见
so this happens not rarely in exploitation
你的能力将有限制
you'll have limited capabilities
不过，如你所见，这些限制通常不足为虑
as you can see often times these limited capabilities aren't that big a deal
你依旧能拿到flag
and you can still get the flag
好吧
alright
希望这是一个有趣的旅程
hopefully this was an interesting journey
这一高级利用系列视频，在这里达到了高潮
this video series for advanced exploitation culminating and putting it all together here
当你未来看到一个任意读、任意写和一个栈地址
when you see in the future an arbitrary read arbitrary write and a stack address
你知道该怎么做了
you know what to do
祝你好运
good luck